I will call it over the regular call to order the regular schedule meeting Miami City Council for Tuesday April 7th, 2026
Public input and schedule personal appearances. We have none
number three approval and presentation of proclamation proclamation declaring
April
2026 as national child abuse prevention month
They started here, you know, we should be number one
All right for a presentation of the boys and girls club summer program
And this our P last summer into our program
but
Certain MSRP kids that have been absorbed into boys and girls club programs
So I just want to go over a couple of things. You have a handout that you can read over
I just want to point out a couple of things for you when we're talking about last summer
So last summer would have been the first summer for MSRP
Joining in with boys and girls club. We served 276
576 kids and you'll see at Miami sites that specifically are two summer locations in Miami which is one of our teen centers downtown, 276 capital from Miami.
56 kids were served at our Fairland location. Part of the reason that we could absorb MSRP is because we opened a third location in the summertime at our new Fairland club that's in the middle of Fairland.
And we were able to move those Fairland kids who were coming to our Miami facility to their own location in Fairland. It essentially opened up the space at our Miami locations to absorb MSRP into what we were doing at the club.
So those 56 kids are now out at the Fairland location that opened up those spots in our Miami club.
We surveyed the parents. It's about the only way we can get survey data. We all get inundated with surveys so it's kind of hard to get the data that you need but we did it by word of mouth with our parents of the enrolled kids in our summer program last year.
Of those surveyed parents, 89 kids had previously participated in MSRP programming even that prior year or in years past. So 89 of those kids were absorbed in Boys and Girls Club.
Just a couple of stats about the kinds of families we serve at Boys and Girls Club. Last year we had 74 single parent households at our Miami clubs.
46% of those families, of the total families that we serve at our Miami locations are low income families. I like to point that out because a lot of times people like to make assumptions about what Boys and Girls Club is or the kinds of kids we serve or who we are.
But the club is for all kids regardless of your family's socioeconomic status, what side of the town you come from. We serve all kids at the club.
I just wanted to point that out. And then another important stat that I wanted to share with everyone is that 187 parents maintain full time employment while their kids were in our care last summer.
That really, what you guys do in the workforce development in our community, that's workforce support systems in the Boys and Girls Club. That 187 parents can maintain their full time employment because they know their kids are in a safe, supervised location.
They're being fed, they're having fun, they're doing all of those things. So I just wanted to point that out. A couple of other highlights from last summer. We served over 18,000 meals and snacks at Boys and Girls Club.
We serve breakfast, lunch, and an afternoon snack every day to our kids at the club. That's a lot of meals that we pump out. It's important though. We took 43 field trips.
We scholarshiped 59 kids. Now that's not 100% scholarship for all 59 of those kids because the philosophy of Boys and Girls Club is that no kid is limited in their participation by their inability or ability to pay to participate.
But we believe that every family has the ability to contribute something. So very rarely do I scholarship kids 100%. We do of course like our foster kids or kids that are staying at the shelter.
Those kids 100% obviously, but everyone else can contribute something regardless of their socioeconomic status. So if they can contribute $5 for their kid to participate in the club, we'll take it and we'll scholarship the rest.
So 59 kids. Some of the challenges of last summer, as we all experienced, we were short staffed by about 8 full-time staff members. If you equate that to a 1 to 15 ratio that we're required to run at the Boys and Girls Club, that's a potential 120 extra kids we could have served last summer if we could have filled those positions.
So hopefully this summer we're off to a running start. I'm sure you've seen our hiring publicly. The more spots we can fill, the better. We have a new partnership this summer with Cherokee Nation. Cherokee Nation will pay any 16 to 21 year old to work at the Boys and Girls Club 40 hours a week.
They can pay them more than I can pay them. So if you know a tribal kid that's between 16 and 21 and want to work with kids, send them my way because Cherokee Nation will pay.
So that's kind of what last summer looked like. I'll point out for this summer, we have a large goal of serving 350 kids at just our Miami sites. Remember we have a Fairland site too in the summer.
But at our Miami sites we have a goal to serve 350 kids this summer. Our max capacity is 380 kids between Riverview and Teen Center. So we're going to shoot close to our max capacity.
We'll talk a little bit more about that as we go down. But how we talk in Boys and Girls Club language is average daily attendance, not enrollment, because we understand every kid is not going to attend every single day.
It's all about a balancing act of the average number of kids that we serve per day. So if we're shooting to enroll 350 kids, we'll probably average between 275 to 285 a day, which is more than we would have served last year.
Our target age this summer that we're really trying to increase our enrollment is our middle school and high school age youth that we're served, obviously because we have a new Teen Center downtown Miami.
Some things we're working on expanding and providing to that specific age group is early job skills opportunities. We currently have kids that are job shadowing every single day in the community in various fields.
We're doing different community service opportunities a lot with our neighbors in downtown. We have neighbors around there that will call and ask for help with some neighbors behind us if they need help.
Our kids are always willing to jump in, pitch in, clean up yards, help set up chairs for an event, something like that. So providing those community service opportunities.
We had one kid in our program last summer who accumulated over 200 hours of volunteer service. She put it on her college entrance application this last year and was accepted into college.
So that's a big deal to be able to accumulate community service hours as well. And then also just providing those positive mentors specifically to middle school and high school kids is so important to preventing juvenile delinquency and violence in our community.
If they have a safe place that they're fed and they have something productive to do, it alleviates a lot of stress on our community in general.
Some other things that we focus on at Boys and Girls Club is we call them core memory experiences. We're just providing kids core memories in their childhood.
Some big things we have planned this summer is our annual trip to Wonders of Wildlife in Springfield. It's not a cheap trip to Springfield to that experience, but it's a once in a lifetime trip for a lot of our kids.
The entry fee is not cheap and many times these kids will not be able to afford to go, but I make it happen every year through fundraising because I believe going to the largest aquarium in the United States is really important to a child's development.
We also make frequent trips to the Amazium and Crystal Bridges in Bentonville. That's a big one that our kids love. And then locally just using our local resources and leading on our local community partners.
We partner really strongly with the library here in town. They run some programming specifically just for us. Things like Lego League. They do the story time where some of you guys have read books to our little kids.
We have a really awesome library and I'm just really proud to partner with them. It's so easy that our kids can just walk there from the Teen Center and they're just so eager to help develop programs for our kids.
We have so many kids and they have outcomes and outputs that they want to achieve and want to work together and so we're really proud of that partnership.
We also have a partnership with Five Alarm Downtown. Our kids go twice a week to Five Alarm Fitness and they do fitness classes and they've learned CrossFit and they have ran around the block like many of the other CrossFitters do in our town.
They really, really like that. And then our last one is we have a strong partnership with the Tribal Health System. Nutrition education is a big part of what we do at the club.
Channa Morton is a wizard in what she does in developing cooking nutrition, cooking education and nutrition in kids. Her and Jordan Douthat do hands-on cooking classes every single week at all of our club sites.
And so it's a pretty phenomenal program if you've ever seen it. Those two are like the only people I know who can convince kids to eat spinach. But she does it and she does it so well, both of them. That's great.
She hasn't convinced me yet. Yeah, well, put it in the cheese case idea. I bet you know what it is.
So that's another partnership. Here's what we need this summer to kind of make this work between all of us. You see the numbers of what it costs to run our summer program.
That's a lot of money to run a summer program for the amount of kids that we do. Our Boys and Girls Club runs about a million dollar budget a year.
And a lot of it goes to operating the summer program. So first we need to hire 25, between 25 and 35 youth development professionals to pull off summer.
Between our staff that we retain from the school year, pull them into summer, we still need to hire an additional 25 to 35 people to pull off summer program.
That will be fully staffed at all of our locations. And then we'll be in the community raising money for sponsorships and field trips.
Things like Wonders of Wildlife that can cost us upwards of $5,000 just to go there alone.
We get those sponsors in the community so that kids can experience what we call those core memories in childhood.
So that's what summer is going to look like for us. If you guys have any questions, I'm happy to answer them.
Thank you for everything you do. My kiddo goes to Fairland and she absolutely loves it.
And every break it's like, can we go to the club? Can we go to the club?
And so I as a single parent, I appreciate everything you guys do.
Thank you. We love to hear that. Our Fairloom club saves our capacity all the time.
I was scared I wasn't getting in for summer.
Yeah, our Fairloom parents are very well trained to get their enrollment in.
Working on some other communities.
Yes.
Enrollments open for summer if you haven't enrolled.
Thank you.
5A, budget amendment 26-08, moving all police department grant and donation monies to the police department fund.
And requesting to use both work comp carryover and work comp funds to cover the underestimated expense for city insurance.
Crystal, thank you for all your hard work. I know you're trying to get a lot of stuff.
Switch around and move around. We appreciate your efforts.
5B, claims list.
Second.
5C, minutes from the March 17th, 2026, regular meeting.
Parker.
Five D, minutes from the March 31st, 2026, special meeting.
Depp.
Aye.
Thorne.
Jones.
Aye.
Dunkel.
Epstein.
Parker.
Aye.
5E, resolution CC 2026-07 to waive Grosel permit fee for citywide Grosel May 1st, 2nd, 3rd of 2026 and I'll make a motion to approve.
Dunkel.
Aye.
Jones.
Barnes.
Aye.
Five F, authorize the city manager to sign the lease agreement with Josh Reed, Reed's Vinyl Products for the property located at 1320 Newman Road.
Kevin.
This is the second time on the lease.
We went out for an RFP back in September.
We received two proposals.
One of the proposals did not meet the lease in the sense that we are not...
Thank you.
This building, if you don't know what it does, it does two things.
It fills the building, because I always say empty buildings die.
It fills the building.
It fills the buildings.
It fills the leaks.
As a city, we went in and did some improvements on the building.
We found that there was a direct...
I know Josh is a local kid that grew up here trying to get a business going here.
I know he's actually had it on Steve Owens for a while, but he outgrew that spot.
So I think it's an opportunity for him to keep growing his business right here in his hometown.
So I think it's a good opportunity for us to fill the building and also help him in the process.
I'll make a motion to approve.
Jones.
Thank you, Kevin.
5G contract between the Oklahoma Department of Libraries and the City of Miami.
Miami Public Library for the America 250 grant, authorizing the city manager to sign contract, certification, and claim form.
So do we all get a jar of that butter?
One second, we don't turn down grant funds, do we?
H, contract with Titan Stage for Heritage Fest 2026, not to exceed $22,947.52.
Okay.
Hi.
Jones.
Memorandum of understanding with the Ottawa County Farmers Market, authorizing the city manager to sign.
Motion to approve.
Second.
Hi.
5J, memorandum of understanding with the Northeast Oklahoma Soccer Association, authorizing the city manager to sign.
Chuck.
So, I'm really honored that we briefed before you.
The biggest difference this year is from back in November.
Second.
Hi.
Between you and Brian.
Six, other new business updates?
Any of which have risen as opposed to this agenda?
Seven, staff reports.
Any questions on that?
Self-tax report?
Good.
Eight, mayor, council, community announcements.
Zib.
A couple weekends ago, he got us organized around a project to clean up an area.
Leadership Miami Class 28 went out and spent an hour and 20 minutes, picked up 1,500 pounds of trash, made an area look much better than it did before.
So, thanks for calling that out, Zib, and I think we can probably do some more like that.
Nine, city manager communications.
Yes, I just have one trend to ask me to let everybody know that we are moving the Main Street Dinner downtown from June 5th to June 4th.
So, it'll be on Thursday.
Number 10, adjournment.
Motion.
Aye.